on today's video we're going to do a
chocolate sbet Face Off gelato MSA
versus David
litz David litz chocolate sbet is kind
of well famous in ice cream circles it
was the first time a recipe such as that
was put into the public Circle and was
available and since then everybody's
tried to make copy of it and you know
just by changing one ingredient by like
10 G doesn't make it the RIS be yours so
today we're going to make both we're
going to make both gelat minina from
Australia and David litz from the US
we're going to make them both
traditionally so in a churn machine this
would both of these would work
brilliantly in ninja creamies because
the ninja creamy makes almost perfect
sbet of all types you're going to hear
the oven click on and off because I'm
making creme brulee in there but for now
let's look at what we need for each
recipe so for the gelato mesina
chocolate sber you're going to need 650
g of water 200 g of sugar 60 G of
dextrose 25 G of molted dextrin 5 G of
stabilizer and 60 G of cocoa powder for
David leitz chocolate sore you're going
to need 555 G of water 200 g of sugar 75
5 G of cocoa powder 2 G of salt 170 G of
dark chocolate 3 G of vanilla extract so
toight there's no stabilizer in David
lit's recipe I'm going to keep it that
way these aren't my recipes let's keep
them as they meant to be and compare the
results so let's get everything ready
and weighed up for both these recipes
650 g of water 200 g of sugar for gelato
M's recipe the method is slightly
different so what we're going to do is
we need to heat the water up to 40°
Centigrade so let's get that on the hob
now and get that warming up because what
it says is to warm the water up and then
add the dry ingredients at that
temperature and that's to get the cocoa
powder to dissolve nice and quick cocoa
powder breaks down into smaller
particles it doesn't dissolve those
cocoa particles just dissipate
throughout the liquid but it does that
above 40° Centigrade it does it much
better around 50 55° Centigrade but 40
is what the recipe says so in here we're
going to get 200 g of sugar 60 G of
dextrose 25 G of multi dextrin don't
worry if you haven't got these
ingredients we're going to talk about
them a bit
later 25 G 5 G of stabilizer whoa um
let's use that is a lot of a lot of
stabilizer 5 G tarum I don't know if I
said that and finally 60 G of cocoa
powder let's give everything a fighting
chance we're going to use valona here
there we go made a triumphant mess and
we are now going to stir those
together and that is our gelato meina
ready we're going to wait for this water
to C to 40° and then we'll add it
together which it happens to
be which is Handy so 40° water we are
meant to add in our powder right it's
completely mixed the sugar is already
dissolved straight into that 40° water
everything kind of just went so now this
goes back on a hob and we Heat this up
to 85 cenr so 185 F super
dark consistency
is it's pretty thick not going to lie at
this stage it's pretty thick stuff now
now something else that
the instructions say is before you churn
if it's too thick then you need to
agitate it whisk it together or put it
in a blender or whatever so the
likelihood is they know that this is a
thick base so that aside let's quickly
tidy this up and get on to the second
one so we're just going to put that one
there I want to compare the color of the
two before they go and chill down so
what do we we need for David liix 550 g
of
water 555 actually 200 g of sugar all
right so the method for David litz is
totally different so let's
just it says we need to whisk first
375 Ms of the water so 375 it's 180 off
so we got 375 G of our water in here we
need to mix this with sugar 200 g cocoa
powder which is 75 G and
salt pink Himalayan salt that
is um and we need to bring this to a
boil and we need to boil it whilst
whisking for 45 seconds so let's combine
it here now that that's combined let's
get that on hob get it boiling let's
weigh our chocolate 170 G of dark
chocolate this is
60%
hello 170
Gams so there's the chocolate and then
obviously we've got our water we need
some vanilla extract vanilla EXT extract
45 seconds of boiling this is similar to
making my chocolate fudge now if you've
um made any of my chocolate fudge
recipes this is basically how I make it
but with different ingredients um you
super heat and in that case boil the
chocolate to really push those cocoa
flavors forward um so we've done that
now it says to add in our chocolate and
stir until that's melted that took less
than 1 minute um then we need to add our
vanilla extract which is three G and
then finally the remaining 180 g of
water there's a lot of methods in David
leitz recipes that you can transfer to
other recipes like this using that cold
water to cool down this mix from boiling
is a great way to to do it uh you can
also do this with cream um I make many
ice creams I use the cream to bring the
temperature down really nice and fast
you don't need to super heat the cream
um it it helps to denat the proteins in
the cream somewhat depending on the
recipe but it's a great way most people
wouldn't know that you've heated the
cream or not so only once you get into
the science of ice cream and the
intricity of the flavors the denat
protein starts to make a bit of a
difference it's not as thick as gelite
msos are we going to get it in there
maybe you know
me all
right colors the same obviously valona
very dark cocoa powder excellent cocoa
powder one of the best I don't think it
is the best I think it is one of the
best there for me there are four or five
cocoa powders that are Head and
Shoulders above above others um but I'll
do our top five coco powder video one
day so let's get these chilled down and
then we can churn them up so first one
to come out the fridge is gelatin a
super thick base it's kind of like
pudding actually textures so it really
needs to be mixed up together before you
put in your machine it may even be too
thick for some of the lower cost home
machines anyway Jed we're going to put
this one in this cream tub so remember
that for later on I'll make sure that we
talk about which one it is during the
eating phase and the next one is David
liit it's a much more traditional kind
of consistency and viscosity if anything
actually it's a little bit thin but hey
Beggars can't be choosers so in the
machine that goes we're going to churn
this exactly the same situation and this
one's going to go in this blue tub and
then we're going to get all of these in
the freezer to harden off for I think
probably at 12 hours so here we are
we're going to scoop up the gelato mimon
first breaking apart when it's being
scooped up which is not a good start and
it's got some kind of weird textural
issues going on and on to David leitz
and it Scoops much more traditionally
it's got a really nice kind of glossy
finish much more even finish and it
looks much more like a traditional
chocolate sbet or to be fair any sbet
should look so now let's try them and
see what they're
like so there we go gelato Ms versus
David liit something to note in that
scoop is the gelato Masina had a really
dry scoop it it had a very strange
scooping texture David litz had a much
more traditional scooping texture so
let's see what they taste like they look
quite similar although yeah look look
the gelatin one just braks apart it's um
hard it's icy which is weird because at
the same time it's
overstabilized you can ignore the IC
because this is sbet
remember the flavor is nice um you know
we've used valona cocoa powder and
that's all that's in there in here we've
got the David Le it one which scooped
much more traditionally it kept together
and it wasn't
dry it
spoons like it should
do much less
ice or much smaller ice crystals I
should
say and The Taste is a very much more
rounded taste so you've got the taste of
that chocolate come through as well as
the cocoa powder
hands down David liit chocolate sbet is
the winner it it's just the breaking
apart of of this which means that
there's there's issues with the solid
content the amount of water 1 kilo of
sbet it's you know five G of stabilizer
just
insane um and that's just to account for
the lack of solids that's what the mold
detection is for in the July T Casino
recipe
multiex in kind of think of that as a
low sweetness
sugar um it's manufactured during the
starch production
process so part of that whole
carbohydrate family um and you use
multiexon to boost solids content and
give you a better mouth feel but there's
this recipe is lacking so much that it
is just not enough to to get to the
Finish Line whereas
David litz is a much more
rounded recipe with the physical
chocolate in there which is obviously
boosting the solids but it's also
increasing the fat so it's giving you a
better mouth feel um that gives it a
better texture better scooping and
serving
texture and overall just a much much
better chocolate sbet so us
wins by quite a margin too gelato Ms I
think they're they're great their social
media is good their flavor names are
great um obviously these are just
recipes that are done in recipe books
something to remember is those recipes
are not what they serve in their stores
so this is a book based recipe
comparison rather than anything else
because David Le doesn't have any scoop
shops but that aside if you're going to
make a chocolate sbet use David leitz
recipe as opposed to gelato ms's recipe
I'm going to do lots more comparison
videos and I'm also going to start
picking holes in other people's recipes
online because I'm I'm getting people
send me recipes asking why they don't
work and they're straight from Tik Tok
and I'm not surprised they don't work so
we're going to start looking at those as
well anyway thanks very much for
watching don't forget to like And
subscribe and I will see you next time
[Music]